A Guide to the Carl Max Lindner, Sr., Architectural Drawings and Plans, 1923-1952
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Carl Max Lindner, Sr., Architectural drawings and plans, 1923-1952
Library of Virginia
41527, 42255, 44576
Accession 41527 consists of 67 sheets, primarily pencil and paper, some blueprints (107 x 79 cm. and smaller); Accession 42255 consists of 175 sheets, primarily pencil and paper, some blueprints and linens (94 x 61 cm. and smaller); Accession 44576 consists of 11 sheets, blueprints (95.25 x 91 cm. and smaller), and specifications (52 leaves).
Carl Max Lindner, Sr.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Carl Max Lindner, Jr., Richmond, Virginia, 4 November 2004 (Accession 41527); Gift of Carl Max Lindner, Jr., Richmond, Virginia, 22 August 2005 (Accession 42255).
Gift of William A. Royall and Pamela Kiecker, Richmond, Virginia, 19 October 2009 (Accession 44576).
Biographical/Historical Information
Carl Max Lindner, Sr. (1895-1973), a Richmond, Virginia, native, learned the architectural profession while working for his uncle, Carl Ruehrmund. A graduate of Richmond's Virginia Mechanical Institute, Lindner began private practice around 1919. Most notably associated with Charles H. Phillips in the early 1920s, Lindner also partnered with Bascom J. Rowlett and Ivan Alten. On a number of commissions, Lindner and Phillips are listed as architects and contractors, a consequence of their being involved in a number of speculative projects.
As an architect, Carl M. Lindner practiced in a number of styles including Art Deco, Tudor, Colonial Revival, Cotswold, and California Mission. A few of Lindner's notable commissions are the Lord Fairfax Apartments (1923), 3117-3133 Monument Avenue (all 1928), and 306 East Grace Street (1928).
Scope and Content
Accession 41527 consists of five sets of architectural drawings by Richmond, Virginia, architect Carl M. Lindner, Sr. Four of the commissions were executed by Lindner; the fifth set depicting the rebuilt Governor's Palace at Williamsburg is by the Boston firm of Perry, Shaw & Hepburn. These blueprint copies are a reference work that Lindner held in his office. The four projects by Lindner include residences for Dr. Randolph Elam, a dentist, in Hampton Gardens, Virginia; Mrs. John T. Wilson, Richmond; Mr. Leon L. Strause, Richmond; and alterations to a Sunday School building for St. John's Evangelical and Reformed Church (now St. John's United Church of Christ), Richmond.
Accession 42255 consists of eleven sets of architectural drawings by Lindner. The projects include drawings for Mr. Philip Strause, Westover Road, Richmond, Virginia; Mr. Morton G. Thalhimer, Monument Avenue, Richmond; nine residences on Monument Avenue, Richmond; Mr. Herbert Hill, Hampton Garden, Virginia; Mrs. C. M. Lindner, Richmond; Mr. and Mrs. C. M. Lindner, Westham, Virginia; Mr. A. L. McClellan, Hampton Gardens; Mr. M. D. Nunnally, Jr., Windsor Farms, Virginia; Ms. M. M. Kratz, Richmond; Mr. Carl M. Lindner, Grove Avenue, Richmond; Mr. C. A. Baylor, Hampton Gardens.
Accession 44576 consists of seven sheets of architectural drawings and specifications (52 leaves) for the residence of Mr. and Mrs. J.P. Hummel, Hill Crest by the James, Westhampton [Richmond], Virginia. Also included are 4 landscape architectural drawings of the gardens by Charles F. Gillette. Also available on CD #195 and in photocopy format.
Arrangement
Chronological.
Contents List
- Accessions 41527, 42255., Extent: 16 folders. (Folder 1-16)
  - Residence for Mr. Abraham L. McClellan, Hampton Gardens, VA, October 1923, Dimensions: 76 x 62 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: ink on linen, pencil on paper; Sheets: 15 (Folder 1)
  - [Nine Residences on Monument Ave.], Richmond, VA, February 1925, Dimensions: 84 x 58 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper; Sheets: 19 (Folder 2)
  - Residence for Mr. Leon L. Strause, Monument Ave., Richmond, VA, September 1925, Dimensions: 91 x 61 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper, ink on linen; Sheets: 16 (Folder 3)
  - Residence for Mr. Carl M. Lindner, Grove Ave., Richmond, VA, April 1926, Dimensions: 56 x 61 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper; Sheets: 16 (Folder 4)
  - Residence for Mr. Morton G. Thalhimer, Monument Ave., Richmond, VA, June 1926, Dimensions: 94 x 61 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper; Sheets: 20 (Folder 5)
  - House for Mr. C. A. Baylor, Hampton Gardens, VA, December 1927, Dimensions: 72 x 47 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper, ink on linen; Sheets: 11 (Folder 6)
  - Residence for Mr. Philip Strause, Westover Rd., Richmond, VA, January 1929, Dimensions: 80 x 61 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper, ink on linen; Sheets: 21 (Folder 7)
  - Williamsburg Restoration for the Williamsburg Holding Co.- Governor's Palace, October 1931, Dimensions: 107 x 79 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: Blueprints; Sheets: 10 (Folder 8)
    Drawn By: Perry, Shaw & Hepburn, Architects, 141 Milk St., Boston & Williamsburg, Virginia.
  - Residence for Mrs. John T. Wilson, Richmond, Virginia, January 1936, Dimensions: 53 x 76 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper, ink on linen; Sheets: 18 (Folder 9)
  - Residence for Ms. Madeline M. Kratz, Monument Ave., Richmond, VA, December 1936, Dimensions: 57 x 46 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper; Sheets: 9 (Folder 10)
  - Residence for Mr. Herbert Hill, Hampton Gardens, VA, January 1937, Dimensions: 58 x 41 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper; Sheets: 11 (Folder 11)
  - Residence for Dr. Randolph Elam, Hampton Gardens, Virginia, October 1938, Dimensions: 48 x 65 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper; Sheets: 11 (Folder 12)
  - Residence for Mrs. C. M. Lindner, Westham, VA, April 1949, Dimensions: cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper; Sheets: 16 (Folder 13)
  - Alterations to Sunday School Building for St. John's Evangelical Church, Richmond, Virginia, October 1950, Dimensions: 53 x 89 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper; Sheets: 12 (Folder 14)
  - Residence for Mr. and Mrs. C. M. Lindner, Westham, VA, December 1950, Dimensions: 76 x 46 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper, blueprint; Sheets: 18 (Folder 15)
  - Residence for Mr. Moses D. Nunnally, Jr., Windsor Farms, VA, April 1952, Dimensions: 89 x 53 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: pencil on paper, blueprint; Sheets: 19 (Folder 16)
- Accession 44576., Extent: 2 folders and 1 box.
  - Residence for Mr. and Mrs. J.P. Hummell, Hill Crest by the James, Richmond, VA, 1929-1934, Dimensions: 95.25 x 91 cm. and smaller; Scale: Various; Media: blueprint; Sheets: 11. Also includes 7 photocopies of drawings and 52 leaves of specifications (blueprints and photocopies). Available on CD #195. (Folder 1-2)
  - Specifications (originals and copies) (Box 1)